Spare a thought for the poor babies of this world.
All they're trying to do is to make sense
of everything going around them,
...a never-ending barrage of words and sensations,
...surrounded by a whole world of confusing stimuli.
Yet somehow they managed to put it all together,
...walking and talking within three years.
Babies are learning machines.
Yet judging from the majority of so-called
...'developmental toys and videos',
...they're only capable of understanding music
...if it's delivered in ludicrously simplified doses.
Toy companies turn out bleeping junk,
...shaped like musical instruments under
the guise of making learning fun.
While TV and internet channels
produce musical content
...that is sometimes of shockingly poor quality,
...there's also a strange prejudice against sharp notes.
Uh- What's wrong with sharp notes?
Where we expect babies
...to crack the incredibly complex nuances
and semiotics of speech on the one hand,
...on the other, our musical expectations seem no higher
...than the ability to mimic 'do-re-mi-fa-so-la-ti-do'.
So in this video I'm calling out the
assumptions I think are incorrect,
...and who I think the worst offenders are.
So I should probably mention that my household
has recently expanded to include twin boys
...who are now four months old,
...so I've a horse in this race.
And I'm surprised at the lack of teaching
literature relevant to this age group.
And don't worry, I'm not gonna go crazy on you,
...blasting all nursery rhymes
and musical toys out there.
When well-crafted, they can be
educational and entertaining,
...but I do find myself scratching my head
...when I'm unable to find a glockenspiel
...that has 12 notes to the scale,
...and more than one octave.
I just want to play my babies
the Back to the Future theme!
Okay, here I am in my studio.
Back to the Future.
Let's do this.
Oh God.
So when sharp notes are removed,
...the instrument is suddenly limited to one key:
C major.
And therefore, it's not possible to play a wrong note
...if we're judging by early 19th-century standards.
But why do this?
Well, there're a couple of reasons.
One is marketing.
Adults who don't have any musical training
...will often think that harmonious-sounding
toys are more 'appropriate',
...because Lord knows dissonance is bad for babies!
That they'd interpret this:
Not for what it is, an interesting noise,
...but for something negative and frightening.
...but for something n̴e̴g̸a̸t̸i̵v̷e̷ ̵a̵n̴d̸ ̶f̵r̷i̷g̷h̷t̴e̶n̷i̵n̶g̷.̴.
.̴.̴.̴b̶u̴t̷ ̷f̷o̵r̵ ̴s̴o̶m̵e̴t̷h̸i̵n̸g̸ ṋ̷͉̇̚͝e̷̛̮̗̽͒g̷̝̥͑͑a̶̘͒͛t̷̗̼̆̾͑ǐ̸̳̒v̴̩̜̲̍͝e̵̮͗̂ ̷͇̤̯̉́å̵̢̒̚ṇ̷̭̈͘͠d̷̤̾̓͒ ̴̰͓̒́f̴̌͜r̵̛͉̗͆͋ȉ̶̼̻͌͘ģ̴̖̿̉͘ḩ̶͓̅͠ẗ̵͎̻́͋e̸̡͛͑͜͝n̶̻̊í̶͇̟ͅń̸̨̗͓͝g̷͎̹͎͌́͝.̶̛̬͇̄̇
Well, so far the evidence for this is non-existent.
No matter what chords or melodies I play to my babies,
...I've not yet managed to find a combinations of notes
...that'd upset them in any way whatsoever.
Usually they just stare at me
fascinated with their eyes wide open.
And for the skeptical I'd say this:
Any baby that's ever heard
...a washing machine,
...(electric) fan, hair dryer,
...Hoover or car engine
...has already been subjected to a level of dissonance
...far beyond the capabilities of any acoustic instrument.
And if you've ever driven with your baby in the car
...and he/she didn't totally lose his mind with fear,
...then you're safe to blame some diminished 5ths.
And it's not like you have much choice anyway.
I mean, check out the dissonance of this piece of crap:
Another more understandable assumption
...is that we should start babies off
...only by exposing them to very simple things,
...that the introduction of musical complexity
can happen as they grow older.
But this is a missed opportunity when we
consider how babies learn spoken languages.
Research in this area emphasizes the importance of
...parents speaking or reading directly
to their children as much as possible.
This involves the use of complex
sentences from day one,
...and from this babies pick up a field for language,
...gradually understanding its purpose and its rule sets.
"They can discriminate all the sounds of all languages,"
"...no matter what country we're testing
and what language we're using."
"And that's remarkable, because you and I can't do that."
"We're culture-bound listeners."
"So the question arises:"
"When do those citizens of the world"
"...turn into the language-bound listeners that we are?"
"And the answer? "
"Before their first birthdays."
Here's one study presented by Dr. Anne Fernald,
...the director of the language-learning lab at
the Department of Psychology at Stanford,
...that shows different stages of a child's
development from 18 to 30 months.
This example is of a child whose parents
regularly spoke to him from birth.
"And you're going to see"
"...how he picks up speed in understanding."
"You'll see the stimulus underneath his picture."
"When the dots are red, he's on the wrong picture."
"When the dots are blue, he's moved to the right picture."
"Where's the doggy?"
"Can you see it?"
"Hey, pretty good."
"Next step: 30 months."
"Uh, It's great."
"He- he- he-"
"...he nails it, and he knows it,"
"...and gives this cocky little smile."
"Where's the doggy?"
"Can you find it?"
We can see here that he's already
begun to jump ahead of the request
...because he doesn't need to ponder
the meaning of the first two words
..."Where's the".
He's gone as far as to deduce
the direction of the sentence
...and has then combined it with a lightning-quick
assessment of his surroundings.
"I'm being told to look for something."
"I bet it will pop up on this screen."
With a wider vocabulary,
...he's able to dedicate his brain to new problems.
So with all this in mind,
...are we really saying that children with
this level of brain sophistication
...can't handle five extra notes?
Should we not be exposing them as quickly as possible
...to all kinds of keys, chord combinations and patterns,
...so that they develop the
same level of musical intuition
...during this unique, once-in-a-lifetime learning period?
In fact, why even expose them to only Western tonality?
Why not Persian tonality,
...the gamelan,
...Vietnamese chamber music,
...microtonality, etc. etc.?
Well, thankfully we don't have to
leave that question unanswered.
It's with the similar frame of mind
...that the musician Rick Beato decided to
document his experiments with his own children,
...playing them an hour of
complex music a day from birth.
He found that doing this resulted in a dramatic
improvement in his child's musical intuition.
He since released numerous videos
...where his son displays an astonishing level
of tonal recognition and perfect pitch.
Beato: Give me the G minor chord.
Dylan: G, B-flat, D!
Beato: And say the names of the notes in...
[plays] ...this one.
Dylan: E, C, D, G, A, F-sharp!
So moving on,
...judging from a large portion of the products out there,
...another assumption that seems to underpin
commercial attitude towards musical education
...is that quality doesn't really matter
because babies don't know any better.
I've already mentioned those toys
with cheap squawking speakers,
...but what about nursery rhyme channels on YouTube?
Again, the quality here varies massively.
Case in point, hooplakidz,
...a channel with millions of views and subscribers.
Channels like this are a dime a dozen
because the music is all public domain,
...and all that's required is L-grade animation
...to convince parents it's worth watching.
I mean, look at the state of that bell!
Hopefully babies can take warped
perspective with a grain of salt,
...but there's loads of other lazy errors and
problematic decision-making going on here.
Let's start with the minor one.
"The wheels on the bus go round and round,"
"round and round, round and round."
"all day long"
So did you hear it?
Well, the first bit is fine,
...but then they go rogue
...by shifting into what's called a relative minor key.
I don't really understand this.
When you repeat the phrase in minor,
...it sounds pensive,
...as if new information has just been delivered.
I mean,
...our baby's meant to whether the wheels
are really turning round and round.
Is this a dark reimagining?
For those thinking,
"This is just pointless nitpicking",
Um...
How do I say this?
Uh, go to the back of the classroom,
...uh, I've ordered your dunce hat.
If the creators of children's programming
...don't understand basic harmonic grammar
...and how musical language is constructed,
...then who knows what sort of bad lessons they're
accidentally passing on to highly-attentive babies.
Let's look at hooplakidz's version of 'Five Little Ducks',
...a staple tune in teaching kids to count.
"Five little ducks went swimming one day,"
"over the hills and far away."
"Mommy duck said, 'quack, quack, quack, quack,' "
"but only four little ducks came back."
Okay well, zipping forward,
...I hope I'm not spoiling the surprise
when I tell you that this keeps happening.
Each time the ducks come back,
...there's one less.
And eventually, none come back.
Then they give you this creepy existential absurdity:
"No little ducks went swimming one day,"
"over the hills and far away."
So I'm not really certain when they've decided to do this.
Normally the format of the rhyme changes here
...with the mother duck getting off
her arse to find the babies herself.
It's not like they had to write anything new,
...and then they went and altered the ending.
"Daddy duck said, 'quack, quack, quack, quack.' "
"and all these five little ducks came back."
Oh, fantastic,
...and now we're enforcing gender stereotypes too.
It takes the authority of a daddy
duck to keep everyone in line.
So, in conclusion,
...when babies are able to eat,
...you don't start them off with fast food.
When teaching them to speak,
...you don't teach them slang or garbled pronunciation.
And if you came across a YouTube
channel that claims to help babies speak,
...and it pronounced things like
or
...then you think this isn't good enough.
So here are three rules of thumb
I'm going to be using from now on:
One, be selective about the stuff that's branded for kids.
A lot of the time, it's just
incredibly low-quality garbage
...made by complacent amateurs
looking to make a bit of money.
Two, don't be afraid to play
music of all types to your kids.
They have learning genius before the age of 1.
And three:
(and I'm literally unable to find
this contradicted anywhere)
Interacting with your children by banging on a drum
...or playing an instrument or singing to them in person
...trumps everything else.
And if they display a love of music down the line,
...you'll know that you gave them
the best possible helping hand.
Now I'm gonna go grab some hoisin
sauce and a few spring onions.
And you can be assured
...that no matter how much you "quack, quack",
...daddy ducks are never coming back, back.